Southwest Folklore Center Video Recordings Collection 1977-ongoing
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Southwest Folklore Center Video Recordings Collection, 1977-ongoing
SWF 010
Southwest Folklore Center
Videorecordings produced and recorded locally by various collectors, depicting Native American poetry readings, dance, music and storytelling performances, chiefly in Tucson and southern Arizona; Mexican-American music; Ukranian folk art; oral histories of Tucson residents; and interviews with cowboy poets, singers, and storytellers. 75 videocassettes.
7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
The Southwest Folklore Center was founded in 1979 upon the dissolution of the University of Arizona Folklore Committee. Since then it has served as an archive for folklore material. Its activities include actively researching and collecting information about Arizona's folk communities, generating outreach programs, and coordinating folk activities throughout the state.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series.
Series I: General Folklore Materials, 1977-1994
Series II: Barrio Historico Interviews, 1990
Series III: Arco Iris Association Productions, 1989-1992
Scope and Content Note
These videos document a range of folkways, chiefly of the Sonoran region. General folklore materials include interviews with Alexandra Romanenko, creator of Ukranian Easter eggs; Stefan Tkachyk, Ukranian wood-carver; and cowboy singers, poets, and storytellers. A tribute in honor of Lalo Guerrero includes performances by several celebrities of music, movies, and television. Other materials include a performance by the Gu-Achi Fiddlers and a presentation by the Richey Elementary School children in cooperation with the San Ignacio Yaqui Council.
Arco Iris Association materials consist of productions of arts programming that reflect ethnic diversity and intergenerational interaction. These include four years of the annual Evening of Native American Expressions productions. The programs consist of performances by professional and student artists, including N. Scott Momaday, Joy Harjo, Chesley Wilson, Mary Redhouse Howard, and Doreen Seton. Also present is master footage of the 1990 Waila Festival with music, food, artists, and traditional dances of the Tohono O'odham. Other productions include various storytelling workshops for children.
The Barrio Historico (Tucson, Arizona) interviews were created during 1990 by Kathryn Wilde, a resident of the barrio. She videotaped interviews with eighteen people who lived in the Barrio Historico area between 1910 and 1990; however, the recollections chiefly concern the 1930s and 1940s. Residents reminisce about the neigborhood, their way of life, school experiences, celebrations, and more. The interviews with Irene Brown, Lalo Guerrero, Arturo Carrillo Strong, Henry Oyama, and Henry Garcia are especially informative.
Yaqui Indians -- Arizona -- Folklore.; Yaqui poetry -- Arizona.; Tohono O'Odham Indians -- Music.; American literature -- Indian authors.; Mexican Americans -- Music.; Cowboys -- Arizona.; Cowboys' writings, American.; Indians of North America.; Tucson (Ariz.) -- Social life and customs.; Mexican Americans -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Social life and customs.; Easter eggs -- Ukraine.; Tucson (Ariz.).; Richey Elementary School -- Tucson (Ariz.).; Barrio Historicio -- Tucson (Ariz.).
Container List
- General Folkore Materials, 1977-1994; Series I:
  Includes videos of student performances of Yaqui poetry and dance, performances by Tohono O'odham fiddlers, Mexican-American music by celebrities in a tribute to Lalo Guerrero; and interviews with Ukranian folk artists and cowboy singers, poets, and storytellers. Materials are organized chronologically by date of performance. Series includes 31 videocassettes, 1/2 inch and 3/4 inch VHS formats.
  - Van Holyoak, Holyoak ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977; Subseries 1
    Video recordings of Van Holyoak working at his ranch in Clay Springs, Ariz. V.1 is a 15 minute show that appeared on television as part of the Folio show with host Dick Gallagher; created from material on V.2 through V.13. V.2 through V.13 contain footage of various aspects of ranch life including riding horseback, cooking over a campfire, rounding up and branding cattle, and repairing a windmill. V.2 includes a brief interview by Jim Griffith concerning settlement of the Clay Springs area and the development of Holyoak's songs and singing. VHS format. Collected by James S. Griffith. Clay Springs, Ariz. 13 videocassettes (ca. 260 min.): sd., col.; 3/4 in.
    - Videotape of 15 min. profile of Van Holyoak shown on Folio television show, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V1)
    - Footage of Van on horseback with interview by Jim Griffith about history of settlement of Clay Springs, Ariz. and development of Holyoak's songs, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V2)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V3)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V4)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V5)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V6)
    - Cattle roundup and calf branding scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V7)
    - Cattle roundup and calf branding scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V8)
    - Scenes of Clay Springs, Ariz. and Van sings while driving his truck, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V9)
    - Scenes of Clay Springs, Ariz. and Van sings while driving his truck, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V10)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V11)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V12)
    - Ranch scenes, March 17-20, 1977 (Box 77.1, Folder V13)
  - Gardner, Gail, George B. German, Glenn Ohrlin, and Van Holyoak, Cowboy singers and songwriters interviews, April 21, 1979; Subseries 2
    Video recordings of informal interviews with cowboy poets, singers, and songwriters discussing their musical beginnings, singing songs, and telling stories. V.1 includes Gardner singing his well-known song "The Sierry Petes" and describing Prescott, Ariz. at the turn of the century. George German talks about gathering songs, rancher and songwriter Romaine Loudermilk, and sings "The Big Corral". Glenn Ohrlin sings Loudermilk's song "Crossover Lee's Ferry." V.2 contains Griffith's interview with George German, who also sings "Riding Old Paint", and with Ohrlin who sings various songs. V.3 and V.4 are different views of V.1 and V.2. Ohrlin visits with Holyoak about cattle ranching and storytelling on V.5. An edited, dubbed version with introductory material by Jim Griffith is on V.6. Gail Gardner, cowboy poet, George German, western radio singer, Glenn Orhlin, cowboy singer, and Van Holyoak, cowboy storyteller and poet; interviewed by Jim Griffith, folklorist, at his home prior to a public performance. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 6 videocassettes (ca. 200 min.): sd., col.; 3/4 in.
    - Interview by Jim Griffith of Gail Gardner; sings and relates story behind writing the song "Sierry Petes". Interview with George B. German about gathering cowboy songs. He sings "The Big Corral". Glenn Ohrlin sings "Crossover Lee's Ferry", April 21, 1979 (Box 79.1, Folder V1)
    - More interview of George German by Jim Griffith. German sings "Riding Old Paint". Glenn Ohrlin sings various songs and talks about his musical background, April 21, 1979 (Box 79.1, Folder V2)
    - Another view of V.1 and V.2, April 21, 1979 (Box 79.1, Folder V3)
    - Another view of V.1 and V.2, 1977-1994 (Box 79.1, Folder V4)
    - Glenn Ohrlin visits with Van Holyoak about cattle ranching and storytelling. Holyoak tells stories, April 21, 1979 (Box 79.1, Folder V5)
    - Edited, dubbed version with introduction by Jim Griffith, April 21, 1979 (Box 79.1, Folder V6)
  - Alexandra Romanenko, Ukranian pysanky interviews, April 28-May 25, 1982; Subseries 3
    Romanenko explains and demonstrates the making of Ukranian Easter eggs, or pysanky. In V.1 she describes how colors, symbols, and design combine to create the meaning of each egg. Many examples are displayed. V.2 and V.3 contain Romanenko's experiences in the Ukraine during World War I and World War II, and she demonstrates and explains how to create pysanky. V. 4 is an edited, dubbed version of V.1 through V.3 created by Jim Griffith, Southwest Folklore Center. Alexandra Romanenko; interviewed by Jim Griffith. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 4 videocassettes (80 min.): sd., col.; 3/4 in.
    - Interview of Romanenko by Jim Griffith. She talks about use of colors, symbols, and design in combination to create meaning of each Ukranian Easter egg, April 28-May 25, 1982 (Box 83.3, Folder V1)
    - She talks about her experiences in the Ukraine during World War I and II while demonstrating how to create eggs, April 28-May 25, 1982 (Box 83.3, Folder V2)
    - She talks about her experiences in the Ukraine during World War I and II while demonstrating how to create eggs, April 28-May 25, 1982 (Box 83.3, Folder V3)
    - Edited, dubbed version narrated by Jim Griffith, April 28-May 25, 1982 (Box 83.3, Folder V4)
  - Stefan Tkachyk, Ukranian wood carving interview, 1984; Subseries 4
    Tkachyk first learned his wood-carving skills while a U.S. prisoner of war in World War II. He explains and demonstrates Ukranian wood-carving, including the uses of different tools, and wood staining and beading. V.2 is an edited version of V.1 created by Jim Griffith for the Southwest Folklore Center. Stefan Tkachyk, wood-carver; interviewed by Jim Griffith. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 2 videocassettes (30 min.): sd., col.; 3/4 in.
    - Explains and demonstrates Ukranian wood-carving, 1984 (Box 84.1, Folder V1)
    - Edited version, narrated by Jim Griffith, 1984 (Box 84.1, Folder V2)
  - Project Choki, 1987-1988; Subseries 5
    Bwia Toli performance preparations, 1987 Oct. 28. Students rehearse program of two plays representing Yaqui folklore, learn about Yaqui culture, and make masks and other materials for their performance. Videos of the resulting performances in this series are at SWF 90.9/V.2 and SWF 90.9/V.3. Project Choki was funded by an Arizona Humanities Council grant to teach students about Yaqui culture. Richey School students and teachers. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz., 1987. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    Christmas performance - Bwia Toli, 1987 Dec.. Christmas holiday program at Richey School. Includes Christmas songs and Project Choki program of two plays representing Yaqui folklore, Bwia Toli and U Kuvahe, and poetry by the students. Also includes discussion among teachers, parents, and contributors to the project following the show. Project Choki was funded by an Arizona Humanities Council grant to teach students about Yaqui culture. The Project Choki segment was later presented to the San Ignacio Yaqui Council; related film at SWF 90.9/V.3. Richey Elementary School students and teachers. Collected by Christine Bixler. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz., 1987. 1 videocassette (ca. 120 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    Bwia Toli: An evening of Yaqui folklore, 1988 Jan. 20. For the San Ignacio Yaqui Council, the students perform two plays, Bwia Toli and U Kuvahe, and read poetry created through Project Choki. The project was funded by an Arizona Humanities Council grant to teach students about Yaqui culture. Yaqui deer dancers also perform. Related films at SWF 90.9/V.1 and SWF 90.9/V.2. Charlie Delgado, producer, and Richey Elementary Students, performers. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz., 1988. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    - Rehearsal for program by Richey Elementary School children, October 28, 1987 (Box 90.9, Folder V1)
    - Christmas performance of program includes holiday songs, Yaqui poetry by students, and two plays from Yaqui folklore, Bwia Toli and U Kuvahe, December 1987 (Box 90.9, Folder V2)
    - Students perform the two plays and read their poetry for the San Ignacio Yaqui Council, January 20, 1988 (Box 90.9, Folder V3)
  - Lalo Guerrero, Tribute to Lalo and Amigos, October 11, 1992; Subseries 6
    Gala tribute to Lalo Guerrero and his band, Amigos with many well-known performers.Singers, musicians, comedians, actors, and actresses perform including Paul Rodriguez and Linda Ronstadt. Palm Springs, Calif., 1992. 2 videocassettes (ca. 180 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in. Some tracking problems noted. Collected by Lalo Guerrrero.
    - Gala tribute to Guerrero and his band, Amigos performed by celebrities from music, movies, and television including Linda Ronstadt and Paul Rodriguez, October 11, 1992 (Box 92.23, Folder V1)
    - Gala tribute to Guerrero and his band, Amigos performed by celebrities from music, movies, and television including Linda Ronstadt and Paul Rodriguez, October 11, 1992 (Box 92.23, Folder V2)
  - Gu-Achi Fiddlers, 1990 Festival of American Fiddle Tunes, Subseries 7
    On-stage performance at American Fiddle Tunes Festival. Gu-Achi Fiddlers, Tohono O'odham band. Collected by Glenn Michael Alessi. VHS format. 1 videocassette (ca. 60 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    - Tohono O'Odham musicians in an on-stage performance at American Fiddle Tunes Festival, 1990 (Box 94.7, Folder V1)
- Barrio Historico Interviews, 1990; Series II
  Interviews with residents who lived in Barrio Historico between 1910 and 1990. Their reminiscences chiefly concern the 1930s and 1940s in Tucson. Some interviews are in Spanish. Series is arranged chronologically by date of interview. Includes 18 videocassettes in 1/2 inch VHS format.
  - A Walk through Barrio Historico, 1990-1991; Subseries 1
    V1. Two separate oral history interviews concerning recollections of barrio life, 1920s to present. Angela was interviewed June 4th; Carlos, on June 15th. Both interviews are in Spanish; handwritten translations are available. Carlos and Angela Montoya, husband and wife; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. Collected by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V2. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1915 to present. Richard Camacho; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 60 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V3. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, ca. 1910 to present. Interview with Trejo is in Spanish. Carmen Trejo and daughter, Mary Estrada; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 45 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V4. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life from 1968 to present, including schools, neighbors, and lifestyle. Suey Gee; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 20 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V5. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life and changes in the barrio in the 1980s. Jose Valenzuela, manager of La Providencia, a store located in the barrio; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 30 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in. V6.
    V6. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1923 to 1990, including neighbors and lifestyles. Arnulfo Trejo; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (39 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V7. Oral history interview with Armando concerns recollections of barrio life, 1940 to present. Guadalupe relates present conditions in barrio. Armando and Guadalupe Montano; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 60 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V8. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930s to 1940s, and changes from then to present. Humberto and Viola Soto, husband and wife; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V9. Two oral history interviews concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930s to present, including family history, neighbors, lifestyle, and changes in the barrio. John and Bertha Esparza, husband and wife; interviewed by Kathyrn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 60 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V10. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930s to 1940s, including family history, schools, neighbors, and lifestyle. Belen Ramirez; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V11. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1916 to 1930s, including schools, neighbors, lifestyle, and relates his early musical development in Tucson. Guerrero also sings several songs which he wrote about Tucson and Barrio Historico. Lalo Guerrero; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 120 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V12. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, ca. 1925 to present, including neighbors, lifestyle, schools, and events. Some portions in Spanish. Maria Trujillo; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V13. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life from 1920s to present. Describes in detail life in barrio, people, events, social life and customs, ethnic groups, musicians, and discusses changes in barrio over time. Henry Garcia; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VSH format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 120 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V14. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930s to 1940s, including family history, neighbors, lifestyle, and events. Arturo Strong; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 120 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V15. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, ca. 1925 to 1990. Mary Soto and daughter, Magdalena Valencia; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 60 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    V16. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930 to present. Discusses neighbors, events and lifestyle. Also relates experiences when evacuated to War Authority Relocation camp near Parker, Ariz., and later U.S. Army service during World War II. Henry Oyama; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    V17. Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, ca. 1915 to present, including schools, neighbors, and lifestyle. Viola Zepeda; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 90 min.): sd., col.: 1/2 in.
    Oral history interview concerning recollections of barrio life, 1930 to 1958, including schools, San Cosmes Chapel, Dia San Juan Bautista celebration, the Santa Cruz River, neighbors, lifestyle, and more. Irene Brown; interviewed by Kathryn Wilde. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 1 videocassette (ca. 120 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    - Carlos and Angela Montoya; in Spanish, June 1-4, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V1)
    - Richard O. Camacho, June 7, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V2)
    - Carmen S. Trejo and daughter, Mary Estrada; Trejo interview in Spanish, June 11, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V3)
    - Suey L. Gee, June 20, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V4)
    - Jose Valenzuela, June 20, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V5)
    - Arnulfo D. Trejo, June 19, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V6)
    - Armando and Guadalupe Montano, June 23, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V7)
    - Humberto M. and Viola T. Soto, July 3, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V8)
    - John and Bertha Esparza, July 5, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V9)
    - Belen R. Ramirez, July 5, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V10)
    - Lalo Guerrero, July 9, 1991 (Box 92.6, Folder V11)
    - Maria M. Trujillo; portions in Spanish, July 18, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V12)
    - Henry Garcia, July 24, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V13)
    - Arturo C. Strong, August 3, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V14)
    - Mary Soto and daughter, Magdalena Valencia, August 16, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V15)
    - Henry Oyama, August 17, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V16)
    - Viola Zepeda, August 24, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V17)
    - Irene A. Brown, August 30, 1990 (Box 92.6, Folder V18)
- Arco Iris Association Productions, 1989-1992; Series III
  Videotapes produced by Arco Iris Productions. Includes four years of annual Evening of Native American Expressions (ENAE) productions, the 1990 Waila Festival, and various storytelling workshops. The 1989 ENAE includes performances by Joy Harjo, N. Scott Momaday, Joy Mihesuah, George Thomas, and the San Xavier Preschool Dancers. Chesley Wilson and student writers and poets of ArtsReach perform in 1990. At the 1991 ENAE program, performers include Chesley Wilson, Mary Redhouse Howard, Doreen Seton, the San Xavier Preschool Dancers, and the Richey Elementary School students. The 1992 ENAE program included Doreen Seton, Danny Lopez, Mary Redhouse Howard, Chesley Wilson, and others. Series is arranged chronologically by date of performance. Includes 26 videocassettes, 1/2 inch VHS format.
  - Waila Festival, 1990, Subseries 1
    Festival of Waila music, food, artists, and traditional dances of the Tohono O'odham. Consists mostly of music, bands, and dancing at the festival. Also includes interviews with Tohono O'odham elders concerning their recollections of past Waila celebrations, an interview with Angelo Joaquin, Sr. concerning the evolution of Waila music from the late 1800s to the present day, discussion between Robert Garfias and band members about the music and interviews with artists about their work. A 90-minute, edited version created from these tapes is available at SWF 93.27/V.4. Participants include Angelo Joaquin, Sr., chairman; Angelo Joaquin, Jr., festival director; Tohono O'odham elders; The American Indians, John Manuel and Simon Cruz, bandleaders; The O'odham Sunliners, Mandro Jose, bandleader; The Tohono O'odham Band, Henry Juan, bandleader; The Santa Rosa Band, Homer Marks, Sr., bandleader; Robert Garfias, ethnomusicologist; Frances Manuel, basketmaker; Ascencio Antone, woodcarver; Mike Chiago, painter; John Reno, jeweler; and Leonard Chana, painter. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 6 videocassettes (ca. 360 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
    - Interviews with Tohono O'odham elders by Daniel Joachin and Danny Lopez; mostly in Tohono O'odham language, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V1)
    - Interviews with Tohono O'odham musicians with Robert Garfias about their music, and Angelo Joaquin, Sr. concerning evolution of this music from the late 1800s, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V2)
    - Inside footage of Waila Festival includes brief talks with various artists and craftsmen, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V3)
    - Outside footage of food preparation and dancing at the festival, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V4)
    - Inside footage of dancing, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V5)
    - Outside footage of dancing, 1990 (Box 93.25, Folder V6)
  - Evening of Native American Expressions, 1989; Subseries 2
    V1-3. Arts program, presented by Arco Iris, of Native American poetry, music, dance, and storytelling by professional and student artists. Presented at the University of Arizona Senior Ballroom. V.1 contains the master edited version, V.2 is unedited with audio, and V.3 is unedited with no audio. Joshua K. Mihesuah, host; N. Scott Momaday, Joy Harjo, Joy Mihesuah, George Thomas, and the San Xavier Preschool dancers. VHS format. Tucson, Ariz. 3 videocassettes (ca. 360 min.): sd., col.; 1/2 in.